Preliminary Guide to the Thomas Chapin Papers, 1870s-1999 (bulk 1979-1999)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Accessions 2002-0281 and 2003-0125
  - Contents of Box 18: (Box 18)
    - Photographs
      - Saratoga, 1990 (Box 18)
      - Japan, Hawaii, and Barcelona, 1981 (Box 18)
      - Home (Box 18)
      - Thomas and Terri in Vermont, 1987 (Box 18)
      - Newport Festival, Saratoga, 1987 (Box 18)
      - Thomas Chapin Trio (Box 18)
    - [Miscellaneous Materials in Binder] (Box 18)
      Includes business cards, notes, jazz bulletins, and postcards.
    - Chapin's Artwork (Box 18)
  - Contents of Box 19: (Box 19)
    - Slides (Box 19)
      Includes slides from Music Man, 1990
    - Photographs
      - Possible Album Cover Pictures (Box 19)
      - Family Photographs (Box 19)
      - North Shore #2 (Box 19)
  - Contents of Box 20: (Box 20)
    - Photographs
      - North Shore, Feb. 1997 (Box 20)
      - New York Hospital, Oct. 1997 (Box 20)
      - In Harmony Benefit Concert, 1997 (Box 20)
      - Newport, 1995 (Box 20)
      - France, 1994 (Box 20)
      - Knitting Factory, Spain and Hawaii (Box 20)
      - Japan, 1993 (Box 20)
      - Andover Reunion, 1995 (Box 20)
      - Portugal and Norway, 1995 (Box 20)
      - Caracas, Venezuela (Box 20)
  - Contents of Box 21: (Box 21)
    May contain duplicate photographs from earlier boxes.
    - Photographs
      - Newport Jazz in Madarao, Japan, 1993 (Box 21)
      - Spirits Rebellious, 1988 (Box 21)
      - New York City, Dec. 1995 (Box 21)
      - Perugia, Italy, 1996 (Box 21)
      - Japan, 1994 (Box 21)
      - [Miscellaneous Photographs, Oct. 1995] (Box 21)
  - Contents of Box 22: (Box 22)
    - Photographs, slides, rolled negatives
      - Uganda, Jan. 1997 (Box 22)
      - [Terri in New Orleans] (Box 22)
      - Thomas Chapin Trio in Finland (Box 22)
      - [Miscellaneous Friends, 1997] (Box 22)
      - Thomas Chapin Trio in Europe, July 1995 (Box 22)
        Includes photographs from Portugal, France, Norway, and Finland.
      - JVC Jazz Trio, 1994 (Box 22)
      - Film Stills (Box 22)
    - [Buttons with Photos of Thomas and Terri] (Box 22)
  - Contents of Box 23: (Box 23)
    - Photographs
      - Chapin in Saratoga, 1987 (Box 23)
      - Maria and Steve Johns (Box 23)
      - Knitting Factory Dressing Room (Box 23)
      - What is Jazz? Festival, June 1991 (Box 23)
      - After Easter Performance, 1997 (Box 23)
      - Thomas Chapin Trio in Europe, May 1994 (Box 23)
      - New York Hospital, Aug. 1997 (Box 23)
      - Trio and Brass, Bryant Park, July 1997 (Box 23)
      - Trio, Real Artways and Andover, Jan 1997 (Box 23)
      - Japan, [1994-1995] (Box 23)
      - Morocco Negatives (Box 23)
  - Contents of Box 24: (Box 24)
    - Photographs
      - Japan (Box 24)
      - Bryant Park (Box 24)
      - Greenwich Village Festival, 1983 (Box 24)
      - France (Box 24)
        Includes photographs from Paris and Toulon.
      - Chapin in Music Man (Box 24)
      - Finland and Estonia (Box 24)
      - [High School Reunion?] (Box 24)
      - Knitting Factory, June 1990 (Box 24)
      - Photographs with Lionel Hampton (Box 24)
  - Contents of Box 25: (Box 25)
    - Photographs and slides
      - Photographs with Lionel Hampton (Box 25)
      - Pat Jolly and Zasis Photos (Box 25)
      - Early Years (Box 25)
      - Thomas and Terri (Box 25)
      - Filming Chapin for Music Man (Box 25)
      - Memorial for Thomas' Birthday at Home (Box 25)
      - Chapin Performing During Illness, [1997-1998] (Box 25)
      - 880 Club in Hartford, Mar. 1994 (Box 25)
  - Contents of Box 26: (Box 26)
    - Photographs
      - 880 Club Winter Gigs, 1990 (Box 26)
      - Christmas, [1994-1995] (Box 26)
      - During Illness, 1997 (Box 26)
      - Hopkins (Box 26)
      - Saratoga (Box 26)
      - Maine (Box 26)
      - Paris with Terri (Box 26)
    - Written Sheet Music
      - The Knitting Factory Festival, 1991 (Box 26)
      - Chapin's Compositions (Box 26)
      - Thomas Chapin Quartet Music (Box 26)
  - Contents of Box 27: (Box 27)
    - Photographs (Box 27)
      Includes photographs of the trio performing.
    - Written Sheet Music (Box 27)
  - Contents of Box 28: (Box 28)
    - Photographs
      - Thomas Chapin Trio (Box 28)
      - Chapin's X-Rays (Box 28)
  - Contents of Box 29: (Box 29)
    - Life Magazine Article on Jazz Greats (Box 29)
    - Written Sheet Music (Box 29)
    - Clippings (Box 29)
      Includes article about Knitting Factory Tour in New York.
    - Photographs of Thomas Chapin Trio (Box 29)
  - Contents of Box 30: (Box 30)
    - Photographs
      - Chapin and Vernon Frazer Recording Song of Baobab (Box 30)
      - France, 1991 (Box 30)
    - [Chapin's Compositions]
      - A Piece (Box 30)
      - Devil's Hopyard TCT and Strings Master Copy (Box 30)
      - Flute Quartet and Nocturne (Box 30)
      - Rain (Box 30)
      - Lullaby to a Hurting Child (Box 30)
    - TDC Recording Project, [1982-1983] (Box 30)
  - Contents of Box 31: (Box 31)
    - Original Compositions
      - Is There Life on Earth? (Box 31)
      - Ten Compositions, Volume 1 (Box 31)
    - Chapin's Geneology (Box 31)
    - [Miscellaneous Loose Materials] (Box 31)
    - [Brasilian Music Books] (Box 31)
  - Contents of Box 32: (Box 32)
    - [Music Books]
      - Brasillian Music (Box 32)
      - Argentinian Music (Box 32)
      - Irish Music (Box 32)
    - Chapin's Original Compositions (Box 32)
  - Contents of Box 33: (Box 33)
    - Written Music
      - Insomnia (Box 33)
      - Devil's Hopyard (Box 33)
      - Lament ([Planys?]) #1 (Box 33)
      - Hats and Shoes (Box 33)
  - Contents of Box 34: (Box 34)
    - Demo Cassettes without Chapin, (21 cassettes) (Box 34)
  - Contents of Box 35: (Box 35)
    - Demo Cassettes without Chapin, (21 cassettes)
      - Knitting Factory (Box 35)
      - Nightbird Song (Box 35)
  - Contents of Box 36: (Box 36)
    - Demo Cassettes without Chapin, (21 cassettes)
      - Zasis (Box 36)
      - Alborada Latina (Box 36)
      - Knitting Factory (Box 36)
  - Contents of Box 37: (Box 37)
    - Demo Cassettes without Chapin, (21 cassettes)
      - Machine Gun (Box 37)
      - Flamenco Latino Demo (Box 37)
  - Contents of Box 38: (Box 38)
    - Demo Cassettes without Thomas, (21 cassettes) (Box 38)
      Includes Avantango and Alborada Latina.
  - Contents of Box 39: (Box 39)
    - Demo cassettes with Chapin, (21 cassettes) (Box 39)
      Includes recordings with Boris Rayskin.
  - Contents of Box 40: (Box 40)
    - Demo Cassettes with Chapin., (21 cassettes) (Box 40)
      Includes recordings with Mario Pavone and Ned Rotherberg.
  - Contents of Box 41: (Box 41)
    - Demo Cassettes with Thomas, (20 cassettes) (Box 41)
      Includes Spirits Rebellious and Song of Baobab with Vernon Frazer.
  - Contents of Box 42: (Box 42)
    - Demo Cassettes with Thomas, (21 cassettes) (Box 42)
      Includes recording of Chapin on Argentine radio.
  - Contents of Box 43: (Box 43)
    - Demo Cassettes with Chapin, (21 cassettes) (Box 43)
      Includes Spirits Rebellious and Thomas Quartet Compositions.
  - Contents of Box 44: (Box 44)
    - Demo Cassettes with Chapin, (20 cassettes) (Box 44)
      Includes Knitting Factory and Alborada Latina.
  - Contents of Box 45: (Box 45)
    - Demo Cassettes, (21 cassettes) (Box 45)
      Includes Alumni Jazz Recital of Thomas Chapin Trio.
  - Contents of Box 46: (Box 46)
    - Demo Cassettes, (21 cassettes) (Box 46)
      Includes Zasis and 55.
  - Contents of Box 47: (Box 47)
    - Demo Cassettes, (21 cassettes) (Box 47)
      Includes Metal Master and Chapin playing the flute.
  - Contents of Box 48: (Box 48)
    - Demo Cassettes, (21 cassettes) (Box 48)
      Includes Spirits Rebellious and Forgotten Game.
  - Contents of Box 49: (Box 49)
    - Demo Cassettes, (20 cassettes) (Box 49)
      Includes feature of Chapin's music on WBUR in Boston.
  - Contents of Box 50: (Box 50)
    [Audio and video materials may be copied only with donor's permission.]
    - Demo Cassettes and Videos, (9 digital videocassettes) (7 digital audio tapes) (Box 50)
      Includes interview with Chapin regarding Night Bird Song CD.
  - Contents of Box 51: (Box 51)
    - Demo Cassettes without Chapin, (57 cassettes)
      - Zasis Tapes (Box 51)
      - Spirits Rebellious Tapes (Box 51)
      - Brass Tapes, 1992 (Box 51)
      - Spirits Rebellious Tapes (Box 51)
    - Tapes of Interviews of Thomas by Terri, (3 cassettes) (Box 51)
  - Contents of Box 52: (Box 52)
    [Audio and film materials may be copied only with donor's permission.]
    - Demo Cassettes with Chapin, (28 cassettes) (5 film reels)
      - Thomas Chapin Documentaries (Box 52)
      - Live at The Blue Note (Box 52)
      - Avantango (Box 52)
  - Contents of Box 53: (Box 53)
    - Demo cassettes with Chapin, (41 cassettes) (7 CDs) (3 microcassettes)
      - Menagerie Dreams (Box 53)
      - Night Bird Song (Box 53)
  - Contents of Box 54: (Box 54)
    - Video Tapes, (16 VHS videocassettes) (1 Betacam-sp videocassette) (Box 54)
      Includes video of miscellaneous tours as well as Chapin's memorial service.
  - Contents of Box 55: (Box 55)
    - Video Tapes and Cassettes, (19 VHS videocassettes) (3 audio cassettes) (3 8mm films) (Box 55)
      Includes Knitting Factory as well as Thomas Chapin at Duke University, 1992.
  - Contents of Box 56: (Box 56)
    - Video Tapes, (7 Umatic videocassettes) (2 VHS videocassettes) (Box 56)
      Includes Night Bird Song and Music Man.
  - Contents of Box 57: (Box 57)
    - Video Tapes, (19 VHS videocassettes) (1 Umatic videocassette) (Box 57)
      Includes Spirits Rebellious and Motation.
  - Contents of Box 58: (Box 58)
    - Video Tapes, (20 VHS videocassettes) (Box 58)
      Includes Zasis and African Music.
  - Contents of Box 59: (Box 59)
    - Commercially produced CDs, (49 music CDs) (Box 59)
      Includes Chapin's music as well as albums by David Lahm, Vernon Frazer, and others.
  - Contents of Box 60: (Box 60)
    - Commercially Produced LPs, (19 vinyl records) (Box 60)
      Includes Lionel Harris and Machine Gun.
  - Contents of Box 61: (Box 61)
    - Commercially Produced Cassettes, (10 audio cassettes) (Box 61)
    - Video Tapes, (2 VHS videocassettes) (Box 61)
      Includes Spirits Rebellious.
    - Commerically Produced CDs, (7 music CDs) (Box 61)
      Includes Alive.
    - 8" Floppy Disk: Thomas Chapin/Bob Muso mixes and set ups (Box 61)
  - Contents of Box 62: (Box 62)
    - Written Sheet Music (Box 62)
      Includes original pieces by Chapin as well as Voyage by Herbie Hancock.
  - Contents of Box 63: (Box 63)
    - Written Sheet Music (Box 63)
      Thomas Chapin Trio Inventory
    - [Miscellaneous Loose Materials] (Box 63)
  - Contents of Box 64: (Box 64)
    - Collages by Chapin (Box 64)
  - Contents of Box 65: (Box 65)
    - Collages by Chapin (Box 65)
  - Contents of Box 66: (Box 66)
    - Collages by Chapin (Box 66)
  - Contents of Box 67: (Box 67)
    - Collages by Chapin (Box 67)
    - Handmade Greeting Cards (Box 67)
    - Drawings (Box 67)
  - Contents of Box 68: (Box 68)
    - Collages by Chapin (Box 68)
    - [Horoscope] (Box 68)
  - Contents of Box 69: (Box 69)
    - Collages by Chapin (Box 69)
  - Contents of Framed Item 1: (Framed item 1)
    - Collage by Chapin (Box 69)
  - Collages by Chapin (Oversize-box 70)
  - Festival Posters with Chapin's Name (Opaperfolder 2)
  - Festival Posters with Chapin's Name (Oversize-box 70)
  - Festival Posters with Chapin's Name (Oversize-box 70)
  - Festival Posters without Chapin's Name (Oversize-box 70)
  - Thomas Chapin's Radius (Oversize-box 70, Reel 1)
  - Thomas Chapin's Radius (Oversize-box 70, Reel 2)
  - Thomas Chapin's Radius (Oversize-box 70, Reel 3)
  - Thomas Chapin's Tape II, 1983 Apr. 11 (Oversize-box 70, Reel 4)
  - Thomas Chapin's Circles and Spirits Rebellious (Oversize-box 70, Reel 5)
  - Thomas Chapin's Spirits (Reel 6)
    - Rain DN4 (Oversize-box 70)
    - Rain (Oversize-box 70)
  - Number 3 (Oversize-box 70, Reel 7)
  - Thomas Chapin (Reel 8)
    - Squid Fantasy (Oversize-box 70)
    - Dawn DN4 (Oversize-box 70)
    - Dawn (Oversize-box 70)
  - Number 1 (Oversize-box 70, Reel 9)
  - [Untitled] (Oversize-box 70, Reel 10)
  - Master I: Thomas Chapin and Bob Musso (Reel 11)
    - One Man Blues (Oversize-box 70)
    - Jitterbug Waltz (Oversize-box 70)
  - Thomas Chapin, Tape I, 1983 Apr. 11 (Oversize-box 70, Reel 12)
  - Master III: Thomas Chapin and Bob Musso (Reel 13)
    - Egg Hunt (Oversize-box 70)
  - Thomas Chapin, 1983 Apr. 11 (Oversize-box 70, Reel 14)
  - Thomas Chapin: Senior Recital, 1975 May 23 (Oversize-box 70, Reel 15)
  - Music Man by Terri Castillo (Oversize-box 70, Reel 16)
  - Music Man by Terri Castillo (Oversize-box 70, Reel 17)
  - The Present by T. Chapin (Oversize-box 70, Reel 18)
  - Thomas Chapin Master Tape 2, Side B (Oversize-box 70, Reel 19)
    ALACRA records 1017.
  - Thomas Chapin Master Tape 2, Side A (Reel 20)
    - Spirits Rebellious (Oversize-box 70)
    - Rain (Oversize-box 70)
    - Uruburos (Oversize-box 70)
    - Circles (Oversize-box 70)
  - Bob Musso and Thomas Chapin (Reel 21)
    - Invitation (Take 1) (Oversize-box 70)
    - Invitation (Take 2) (Oversize-box 70)
  - Number 2 (Oversize-box 70, Reel 22)
  - Number 4 (Oversize-box 70, Reel 23)
  - Bob Musso and Thomas Chapin Master II (Reel 24)
    - Radius (Oversize-box 70)
    - A January Tear (Take 1) (Oversize-box 70)
  - Thomas Chapin, Nov. 1988 (Reel 25)
    - Spirits (Oversize-box 70)
  - Thomas Chapin (Reel 26)
    - Spirits (Oversize-box 70)
    - Out-Takes from Spirits Rebellious Session, Nov. 1988 (Oversize-box 70)
  - Bob Musso and Thomas Chapin (Reel 27)
    - A January Tear (Take 2) (Oversize-box 70)
  - Thomas Chapin, Producer Bob Musso (Reel 28)
    - Egghunt (pulled to master) (Oversize-box 70)
  - Thomas Chapin, Producer Bob Musso (Reel 29)
    - Jitterbug Waltz (Oversize-box 70)
    - Radius (Oversize-box 70)
  - Thomas Chapin, Producer Bob Musso (Reel 30)
    - Forgotten Game (pulled to master) (Oversize-box 70)
  - Bob Musso and Thomas Chapin (Reel 31)
    - Forgotten Game (Oversize-box 70)
  - Out Takes (Reel 32)
    - Circles (cut to master) (Oversize-box 70)
    - Spirits Rebellious (Oversize-box 70)
  - Thomas Chapin #1, The Present (Oversize-box 70, Reel 33)
  - Bob Musso and Thomas Chapin (Reel 34)
    - Radius (take one) (Oversize-box 70)
    - Radius (take two) (Oversize-box 70)
  - Bob Musso and Thomas Chapin (Reel 35)
    - Egg Hunt, take one (Oversize-box 70)
  - Tom Chapin (Reel 36)
    - Cat's Paw (Oversize-box 70)
    - Sloane (Oversize-box 70)
    - P.A. Stage Band (Oversize-box 70)
  - Rain, New York City [June 1988] (Oversize-box 70, Reel 37)
  - Thomas Chapin, Phillips Academy [1975] (Oversize-box 70, Reel 38)
  - Thomas' Radio Audition for WWUH (Oversize-box 70, Reel 39)
  - Music Man (Oversize-box 70, Reel 40)
Materials Cataloged Separately
The following 11 books were removed from the collection (accession 2001-0157) and cataloged separately.
Glen Alyn, I Say Me for a Parable: The Oral Autobiography of Mance Lipscomb, Texas Bluesman, Da Capo Press, 1993.
Miles Davis with Quincy Troupe, Miles: The Autobiography, Simon and Schuster, 1989.
Vernon Frazer, Relic's Reunions, Beneath the Underground Books, 2000.
Vernon Frazer, Demolition Fedora, Potes & Poets Press Inc., 2000.
Vernon Frazer, Improvisations (I-XXIV), Beneath the Underground Books, 2000.
Vernon Frazer, Sing Me One Song of Evolution, Echolalia Press in association with Beneath the Underground Books, 1998.
Vernon Frazer, A Slick Set of Wheels, Water Row Press, 1987. [Loose materials from inside the book can be found in box 35 of accession 2001-0157 of the Thomas Chapin Papers.]
Vernon Frazer, Stay Tuned to This Channel and other stories, Beneath the Underground Books, 1999.
Lloyd NcNeill, Black Line, Baobab Record Company, 1983.
Charles Mingus, Beneath the Underdog, Penguin Books, 1971.
Herschel Silverman and Steven Dalachinsky, Intervalsss: the poems and words of musicians, Beehive Press and Sisyphus Press, 2000.